System UI booting source code analysis in this section will have a look at how the system UI is booted
and which all classes modules are responsible for voting systems UI.
So let's get started.
So let's first open up the emulator.
And to look at window family.
OK, so the emulator is now up, and here you can see the lock logs.
And here I have filtered with system UI.
So this is just to show you these locks.
So from these locks, we can make out that system UI start is happening from the system.
So, OK, so here you can see systems, our timing starting the system UI and took nine milliseconds
just to trigger this system.
So this is triggered.
It's getting into that package.
So or Android brought system UI.
And then you could see here that the system UI application is constructed for the system.
UI application is created and then there are some timing here where you can see dependency injection
one milliseconds.
So here, basically, system UI uses D'Agata to do some dependency injection.
So here it's basically doing that.
And then later on, it's initializing all these different, different models of system.
You like the other recent module volume UI status bar our UI Ringtone Player Keyboard UI.
And finally, it completed in 860 milliseconds.
So by this time, the system UI is completely up and we got all these same UI modules.
So this how on a very high level, it works.
So now let's get into the code and see how it is actually triggering and which classes are responsible
for what in detail.
So let's now look at the code, how added bookmarks or important execution points.
So as we discussed earlier, the system UI is standard from system server.
So within the system server, it is a function called start other services.
So this is basically the function which start a lot of other services.
System Server is one of the most important parts of Android, and System Server is basically responsible
for starting a lot of services, including system UI, activity management system, window management
system and many, many other services.
So System UI is getting started from start other services, and it's started at this point.
So there is another function called start system.
You want this one to go there.
So this function is pretty important.
What it does is it's a and it's the it's manager internal and then it uses the Get System UI service
component function within that.
So if you go there, it's basically an abstract class.
It's defined within the package manager, Mr. Jarba.
And within that, you can see that it gets the system UI service component from my next summer conflict,
but is nothing but this one config system UI service component.
So that's the one here.
You can see that it's pointing to the OMED or Android or system you want service.
So we started from the system server.
So System Server is having the stock other services, which is actually responsible for calling stock
system UI.
And if you didn't start system you, why we it's an intent.
So here you can see it creates an intent, uses this particular component from the package and it's
a service.
And then it starts the service, as the user with this interpreter also tells Windows Manager.
Add a system UI.
You started by calling these particular functions, or it informs the window manager service.
Add the system UI, you start it.
So in short, the Start System UI basically creates a handle to package manager and from package manager.
It gets the system UI service component, which is nothing but system UI service class.
And with this indent, it cause the system UI service class.
Also, it informs the window manager that the system UI you started that is basically the functionality
of Start System UI.
So now let's go to system you white service.
So within System UI service, it basically extends the service and it has some constructor here and
in the on create the first line, which you can see here, actually, for instance, the stimuli application
class caused this particular function, which is the most important thing which we need to look at.
It also does some other stuffs here, and this is the most important for us.
So let's go there.
Here you can see that it gets the system you white service components and the system UI service components.
It picks up from these configurations config system UI service components.
So let's go inside that so-called fix system UI service components within this system UI service component
that you can see that it has all the system UI components defined.
Basically, we knew all these items and we start them one by one.
Let's see how the system is starting each of this model.
Yeah, and which actually gives us that.
All right.
So here you can see that gets the names.
And with this name, this name is actually passed to start service if needed and within start services
if needed.
You come to the bottom here and see that there is one or which actually loops through all those services
or any similar services dot length.
It goes through one by one starts.
So here you can see on boot completely.
It's also calling on boot complete.
Its own boot completed is nothing but a function from the system new wide or.
The system UI or Java classes are actually inherited by most of the components and extended by most
of these components.
So in short, what happens is that the system starts process from the system.
So the system's Tiwa scores the start system UI from the system and the star system UI.
It actually picks the component and creates an intent and starts the system UI service.
So System UI service and within the system UI.
So reset all system UI application.
And of course, this particular function starts obviously if needed and within the start service needed
it or start services, if needed, functioned as normal function, which actually loops through all
these all these different packages and starts them one by one.
And that's exactly what we are seeing in these logs.
So that's exactly what we are seeing in this block.
So here you can see that it's starting each of these services.
One by one, it will be the same the same sequence as defined.
Yeah, should be starting the notification channel, first notification channel and then the key immediate
key Gavi mediator and then the reasons the recents volume UI that is bar and so on.
In the post, you show.